<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes"?>
<?rfc topblock="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-dfp-00" ipr="none">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="dfp">Domain Federation Protocol</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
      <organization>SAY Media</organization>
    </author>

    <date />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a mechanism for domains to create ad-hoc,
      verified associations and then using these associations to enable
      user-to-user communication between domains. The protocol defined herein
      provides a generalized mechanism for communication between entities on
      different domains, but is intended primarily as a means to allow social
      network users to interact across network and application boundaries.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>The Domain Federation Protocol (DFP) is a protocol for federated
        communication between users or other entities on different domains.
        This protocol creates a verified, unidirectional association between
        two domains and establishes a means of identifying users or other
        entities within these domains, with the goal of enabling social
        networking interactions between said entities.</t>

        <t>DFP is built on similar architectural principles to the Simple Mail
        Transfer Protocol (SMTP) and the Extensible Messaging and Presence
        Protocol (XMPP), but adapts the architectural model for use by
        applications communicating exclusively by Hypertext Transfer Protocol
        (HTTP) messages.</t>

        <t>This protocol is designed primarily for use in asychronous,
        background communications. It is not optimized for scenarios where a
        foreground response to a user is blocked by the completion of this
        protocol.</t>

        <t>This protocol is also designed to establish associations at the
        domain level, meaning that this protocol's efficiency is not degraded
        as more users are added to a given domain. However, since each domain
        pair requires a separate association, it is more efficient on a
        per-user resource investment basis to communicate with a domain with
        many users than a domain with fewer users.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Addressing Scheme">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>An entity is anything that can be considered to have a presence on
        a social network. This includes but is not limited to users,
        organizations and software "bots". An entity is uniquely addressed,
        for the purposes of this protocol, by a <spanx style="emph">node identifier</spanx>
        and a <spanx style="emph">domain identifier</spanx>. For convenience
        these can be serialized into a single string called an <spanx
        style="emph">entity identifier</spanx>.</t>

        <t><spanx style="strong">TODO: write some BNF for this. basically it's the obvious node@domain syntax, with similar syntax constraints to that of email addresses</spanx></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Domain Identifier">
        <t>The domain identifier consists of a fully qualified domain name, as
        defined by <xref target="RFC1035"></xref>. When used in this protocol,
        the domain is in ASCII. However, applications SHOULD accept user input
        of domains in Unicode and present domains to users in Unicode and
        apply the conversions defined in <xref target="RFC3490"></xref> to
        translate to and from the ASCII representation that will be used to
        serialize the domain identifier for use in DFP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Entity Identifier">
        <t>The entity identifier is a name, unique within a particular domain,
        that identifies an entity. An entity identifier is any sequence of
        octets that is considered valid and normalized UTF-8, except that this
        sequence may not contain codepoints U+0020 (space) nor U+0040 (at
        sign). Applications SHOULD reject identifiers that are not valid or
        normalized UTF-8. Given that only normalized UTF-8 is permitted,
        identifiers MAY be compared octet-for-octet internally by
        applications, but identifiers should be displayed to users using the
        unicode characters that result from decoding the octet sequence.</t>

        <t><spanx style="strong">TODO: What is a good thing to reference about normalized UTF-8?</spanx></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="discovery-document"
             title="Retrieving the Discovery Document for a Domain">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>The discovery document for a domain is an HTTP resource that
        describes the federation resources available for a domain. The URL of
        a domain's discovery document is obtained by adding the prefix <spanx
        style="verb">https://</spanx> and the suffix <spanx style="verb">/.well-known/federation</spanx>
        do the domain. This resource MUST respond to an HTTP GET request by
        returning an entity whose <spanx style="verb">Content-Type</spanx> is
        <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx> and whose body is a valid
        JSON object. The properties of this object and their valid values can
        be defined by other specifications. This specification defines one
        initial property in <xref target="domain-dialback"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Clients MUST make use of the standard HTTP caching mechanisms to
        avoid imposing unnecessary load on the target server.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="domain-dialback"
             title="Establishing Domain Associations with Domain Dialback">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>Domain Dialback is a lightweight mechanism by which a target domain
        can verify a request from a source domain and then issue a temporary
        bearer token to the source domain for use in subsequent requests.</t>

        <t>The domain dialback mechanism is made possible by the existence of
        the Domain Name System (DNS), since one server can (normally) discover
        the authoritative server for a given domain.</t>

        <t>Domain dialback is uni-directional, and results in weak
        verification of identity in one direction. Mutual authentication is
        not possible via dialback. Therefore, domain dialback MUST be
        completed in each direction in order to enable bi-directional
        communications between two domains.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Determining the URL of a Domain's Association Endpoint">
        <t>The URL of a domain's association endpoint is declared in the
        domain's discovery document (<xref
        target="discovery-document"></xref>) via the property <spanx
        style="verb">associate</spanx>. Its value is a JSON string containing
        an absolute URL using the <spanx style="verb">https:</spanx>
        scheme.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="request-association" title="Requesting an Association">
        <t>A source domain requests a unidirectional association with a target
        domain by making an HTTP POST request to the target domain's
        association endpoint. The Content-Type of this request is
        application/x-www-form-urlencoded and its payload is the following
        parameters encoded with this encoding scheme:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="mode">The literal string <spanx style="verb">associate</spanx>.</t>

            <t hangText="domain">The source domain.</t>

            <t hangText="verifier">A string, containing only ASCII characters,
            that allows the source domain to uniquely recognize this request
            during verification.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The response to this request is delayed until the dialback process
        is completed, as described in the following section.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verifying an Incoming Association Request">
        <t>A target domain verifies an association request by making an HTTP
        POST request to the target domain's association endpoint. Again, the
        Content-Type of this request is application/x-www-form-urlencoded. Its
        payload is the following parameters:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="mode">The literal string <spanx style="verb">verify</spanx>.</t>

            <t hangText="domain">The target domain.</t>

            <t hangText="verifier">The token provided by the client in the
            association request.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>If the provided domain and token represent a known, outstanding
        association request the source domain responds with a <spanx
        style="verb">200 OK</spanx> response whose Content-Type is <spanx
        style="verb">application/json</spanx> and whose body is a JSON object
        with a single property <spanx style="verb">verifier</spanx>, whose
        value is a JSON string echoing back the verifier. The request is
        <spanx style="emph">not</spanx> verified if the response status is not
        200, if the response body is not a JSON object or if the <spanx
        style="verb">token</spanx> value does not match the expected value.
        Requiring the verifier to be echoed back avoids falsely detecting a
        verified request for resources that return 200 OK unconditionally and
        are not intentionally responding to the verify request.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Responding to the Association Request">
        <t>If the association request is verified, the response to the
        association request has the status <spanx style="verb">200 OK</spanx>
        and the Content-Type <spanx style="verb">application/json</spanx>. The
        body of this response is a JSON object with the following
        properties:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="token">A JSON string containing the bearer token that
            will act as a shared secret allowing the source domain to make
            authenticated requests to the target domain using this
            association.</t>

            <t hangText="expires_in">A JSON integer giving the number of
            seconds after which this association is invalid.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In order to reduce problems related to clock skew or response
        delay, the source domain MUST actually discard created association two
        minutes before the expire time, and the target domain MUST consider
        the association valid for two minutes after the expire time.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Establishing Domain Associations with pre-determined credentials">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>A target domain MAY offer a means by which a source domain can
        establish a relationship out of band of the DFP flow. In this case,
        the target domain issues the source domain a set of credentials which
        it can use in an extended version of the association request. A target
        domain MAY offer additional functionality for associations established
        in this way, for example if the prior relationship was dependent on
        the organisation responsible for the source domain agreeing to terms
        of use that are required for such additional access.</t>

        <t>An existing relationship is identified by a <spanx style="emph">client id</spanx>
        and authenticated via a <spanx style="emph">client secret</spanx>.
        These terms are taken from OAuth 2.0 but in practice the target domain
        may issue any set of credentials it wishes, with no requirement that
        these credentials are also usable in any OAuth 2.0 request.</t>

        <t>If the target domain does verification of domain ownership as part
        of the pre-registration process (using a mechanism that is out of
        scope for this specification), it MAY skip the dialback verification
        process when establishing an association. However, this is not
        required, and a target domain MAY still perform dialback verification
        for association requests that include client credentials, for example
        if the client credentials identify an application or organization but
        not any particular source domain.</t>

        <t>The following parameters are used when supplying client
        credentials, in addition to the parameters specified in <xref
        target="request-association"></xref>, which are all still required in
        this case:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="client_id">An opaque token issued by the target
            domain to identify the requesting application.</t>

            <t hangText="client_secret">A shared secret issued by the target
            domain to use with the provided client_id.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>A target domain MAY require client credentials in order to
        establish an association, in which case it must respond to an
        association request without credentials using a client error HTTP
        response code such as 400 Bad Request. However, such a target domain
        MAY instead grant an association that provides limited access for
        requests without client credentials, allowing limited interoperability
        for clients that have not pre-registered.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Other Mechanisms for Establishing Domain Associations">
      <t>Domain dialback as described in <xref
      target="domain-dialback"></xref> provides a lightweight, generic
      mechanism for establishing an association between two arbitrary domains.
      A pair of domains MAY use an alternative means, not defined by this
      specification, to establish an association. This includes but is not
      limited to a protocol involving use and verification of SSL client
      certificates, or an application-specific domain pre-registration
      procedure.</t>

      <t>Domains SHOULD support domain dialback in order to achieve maximum
      interoperability, but domains MAY consider associations established via
      domain dialback less trustworthy than those established by other means
      and provide differing levels of functionality depending on the mechanism
      used.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="HTTP Message Extensions">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>The sections that follow describe extensions to the Hypertext
        Transfer Protocol (HTTP) that allow an HTTP request to carry a
        verifyable source identity based on a previously-established domain
        association.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The DFPEntity Authentication Scheme">
        <t>This specification establishes a new HTTP authentication scheme
        whose identifier is <spanx style="verb">DFPEntity</spanx>. This scheme
        can be used to act as an entity within a domain using a
        previously-established domain association bearer token.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Authorization: DFPEntity john.smith 1sb25b53534b34:44533]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>An HTTP server supporting this authentication scheme MUST
        determine, via a means outside the scope of this specification, which
        domain the given association bearer token belongs to. If no such
        association exists, authentication fails. If such an association
        exists, the identity of the requester is the entity identified by the
        given entity identifier and the domain identifier corresponding to the
        association bearer token.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <section title="Considerations for Domain Dialback">
        <t>The domain dialback mechanism described in <xref
        target="domain-dialback"></xref> helps prevent against domain
        spoofing, thus making it more difficult to send a message that a
        target will falsely believe to be sent from another sender. It is not
        a mechanism for authenticating, securing or encrypting communications
        between two domains. It is susceptable to DNS poisoning attacks unless
        DNSSEC is used or unless a trustworthy verification of the source
        domain's TLS certificate is possible.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1035">
        <front>
          <title>Domain Names - Implementation and Specification</title>

          <author fullname="P. Mockapetris" initials="P."
                  surname="Mockapetris">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="1987" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3490">
        <front>
          <title>Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications</title>

          <author fullname="Patrik Faltstrom" initials="P."
                  surname="Faltstrom">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2003" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
